<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pon sal</title>
    <description>una pesadilla de lengua</description>
    <link>http://ponsal.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ponsal.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>New Year&#39;s Terms and Conditions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: I translate and reproduce Eduardo Salles’ work in this post. In a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://cultura.elpais.com/cultura/2014/11/28/actualidad/1417138258_495568.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, he said that it’s cool: “Que sus imágenes estén por la red, a veces sin crédito, no le molesta. Para él internet es ‘agarrar, hacer y repetir’.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not acquainted with the work of the Mexican artist Eduardo Salles, you should be. He draws unbelievably clever cartoons on his site &lt;a href=&quot;http://cinismoilustrado.com/&quot;&gt;Cinismo Ilustrado&lt;/a&gt;, which, owing to their relatively small amount of text, can be feasibly enjoyed (rather than slogged through) by language learners. Here, for example, is a simple one in which brands and branded concepts are rendered as wrestling masks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/heroes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;sundays&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salles just put out a list of terms and conditions for the new year, which I really liked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/terms-and-conditions.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;terms and conditions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it’s so text-heavy, I thought I’d take a stab at a translation (uncertainty is marked with [?].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following is an (attempted) translation of Eduardo Salles’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://cinismoilustrado.com/image/106620128073&quot;&gt;work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;new-year&quot;&gt;New Year&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;terms-and-conditions&quot;&gt;Terms and Conditions&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s terms and conditions have changed. Please read the new terms and conditions in order to begin the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a. The New Year does not promise to actualize your intentions, goals, objectives, desires, fantasies, or any other imagined projections. The achievement thereof is your sole responsibility, and is subject to changing circumstances during the year [?].&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
b. The New Year does not promise to fulfill your expectations, whatever they may be. Neither is it subject to fulfill economic, political, social, technological, or cultural predictions.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
c. The New Year is not responsible for losses, sicknesses, bankruptcies, layoffs, weight and size gains, romantic disappointments, existential crises, academic problems, or whatever other misfortune one might suffer during its passage.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
d. The New Year is not obligated to be better than The Old Year. All types of catastrophe – natural (hurricanes, earthquakes, fires, floods) and anthropogenic (armed conflicts, currency devaluations, social instability, and Michael Bay movies) – can happen at any moment.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
e. The conditions of the New Year are subject to change without prior warning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;form class=&quot;new-year-terms&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; name=&quot;terms&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;label name=&quot;terms&quot;&gt;
      I have read and agreed to the terms and conditions of the New Year.
    &lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a class=&quot;button&quot;&gt; Continue &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;a class=&quot;button&quot;&gt; Screw this &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 03:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/translation/2014/12/31/el-ano-nuevo/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/translation/2014/12/31/el-ano-nuevo/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>BBC Mundo Noticias — Resumen De 2014</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://emp.bbc.co.uk/emp/embed/smpEmbed.html?playlist=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bbc.co.uk%2Fmundo%2Fmeta%2Fdps%2F2014%2F12%2Femp%2F141218_video_2014_resumen_noticias2_ms.emp.xml&amp;amp;title=Cu%C3%A1les%20fueron%20las%20noticias%20m%C3%A1s%20impactantes%20de%202014&amp;amp;product=news&amp;amp;lang=es&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2014 03:41:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/video/news/2014/12/29/noticias-del-a%C3%B1o/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/video/news/2014/12/29/noticias-del-a%C3%B1o/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Amigos del Alma and The Pseudocalque</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, common turns of phrase translate word for word (&lt;em&gt;palabra por palabra&lt;/em&gt;). Wikipedia says that this phenomenon is called a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calque&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;calque&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so I’ll be ill-informedly using that term (full disclosure: I don’t know linguistics or anything like that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These parallel expressions get more fun as they get more figurative – your boss will put the brakes on a project, while &lt;em&gt;su jefe pondrá&lt;/em&gt; [will put] &lt;em&gt;freno&lt;/em&gt; [brake] &lt;em&gt;al projecto&lt;/em&gt;. Wikipedia mentions “skyscraper” as an example; in Spanish, they are &lt;em&gt;rascacielos&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;rascar&lt;/em&gt;: v. to scrape, &lt;em&gt;cielo&lt;/em&gt;: n. sky). Calques like these are a blast because they bore holes through walls between languages (or vocabularies, at least), and – for the short span of a synaptic firing – make you feel like you actually understand Spanish or Chinese or whatever. Foreign languages offer many deeper pleasures, but the calque is instantly gratifying. They’re the cotton candy of language learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is the curious case of what – for lack of a better term – you might call pseudocalques. These phrases employ metaphors that resonate across multiple languages, but aren’t word for word matches. They have wrinkles that make you reflect on language a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example: I &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g0FhbwViHiU&quot;&gt;ran across&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;amigo del alma&lt;/em&gt;  yesterday. This translates literally to “friend of the soul”, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wordreference.com/es/en/translation.asp?spen=alma&quot;&gt;can mean&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;(friendship) kindred spirit/very close friend  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;(romantic) soulmate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While “soulmate” is commonly used to describe romantic partners in English, I know of no English construction that describes a friendship between people with form-fitted souls, which is a real shame (Spanish also has &lt;em&gt;hermano de alma&lt;/em&gt;, or “brother of the soul”). In English, you can call someone a “best friend,” but that just ranks them among other friends. You can call someone “like a brother,” but that’s more about loyalty and commitment. “Kindred spirit” is nice, but leaves friendship out of the equation entirely (you’d be sorted into the same bucket as a kindred spirit, but there’s no telling whether or not you’d get along in there). The closest thing I can think of is the antiquated “bosom buddy,” which is just repulsive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s the romantic definition! To a non-native speaker at least, &lt;em&gt;amigo del alma&lt;/em&gt;’s layering of friendly and romantic meanings captures relationships in which your significant other is your best friend. The increasingly popular “partner” gets at this sense a little bit, but certainly introduces businesslike overtones into romantic relationships (which &lt;em&gt;amigos del alma&lt;/em&gt; emphatically does not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will leave a longer post about why American society is afraid of friend soulmates for another day. For now, here is Roberto Carlos singing “Tu Eres Mi Amigo Del Alma”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/hQLjP-HWabw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;see-also&quot;&gt;See also:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This this &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_calques&quot;&gt;list of calques&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2014 04:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2014/12/28/amigo-del-alma/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2014/12/28/amigo-del-alma/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Honduras [noun]</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The upshot of having a 3rd grade vocabulary is that burying your head in the dictionary yields whole lot of notable secondary definitions. Who would have thought, for example, that the Spanish word for wife (&lt;em&gt;esposa&lt;/em&gt;) would turn into &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wordreference.com/es/en/translation.asp?spen=esposas&quot;&gt;handcuffs&lt;/a&gt; when pluralized!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nation of Honduras presents a less hilarious instance of this – &lt;em&gt;honduras&lt;/em&gt; translates to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wordreference.com/es/en/translation.asp?spen=honduras&quot;&gt;depths&lt;/a&gt; (which is a pretty metal name for a country). The name is of uncertain provenance, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honduras#Etymology&quot;&gt;wikipedia says&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The name could either refer to the bay of Trujillo as an anchorage, &lt;em&gt;fondura&lt;/em&gt; in the Leonese dialect of Spanish, or to Columbus’s alleged quote that “Gracias a Dios que hemos salido de esas Honduras” (“Thank God we have departed from those depths”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first scenario, it’s kind of like Honduras and Anchorage are cousins!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I leave you with a map showing the nation of Honduras, with a pin on Trujillo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://www.openstreetmap.org/export/embed.html?bbox=-89.69238281249999%2C12.586732432464062%2C-82.2216796875%2C19.16592425362801&amp;amp;layer=cyclemap&amp;amp;marker=15.897942401022103%2C-85.95703125&quot; style=&quot;border: 1px solid black&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2014 07:53:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2014/12/25/honduras/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2014/12/25/honduras/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sobre Pon Sal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog’s title comes from a little song which taught me various irregular forms of the second person imperative in Spanish. It goes something like this (sung to the tune of jingle bells):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;di haz ve&lt;br /&gt;
di haz ve&lt;br /&gt;
pon sal se ten ven&lt;br /&gt;
di haz ve&lt;br /&gt;
di haz ve&lt;br /&gt;
pon sal se ten ven  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed pretty appropriate with it being Christmas Eve day and all, y eso es.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2014 07:53:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/meta/2014/12/24/sobre-ponsal/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/meta/2014/12/24/sobre-ponsal/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
