<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pon sal</title>
    <description>una pesadilla de lengua</description>
    <link>http://ponsal.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ponsal.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Stop Abusing &quot;Right?.&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;People (myself included) sometimes explain things using a weird semi-interrogative version of the word “right?/.”. It has the upward inflection of a question, but the speaker continues on to the next sentence without leaving space for an answer. Here is a made-up example that should not be taken as historical fact: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So during the Revolutionary War, the Native Americans all sided with the British, since they saw the seceding Americans as enemies, right?. [sic] And so the question is…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This construction aggravates me. The inflection on “right” suggests that there could be disagreement over the topic, but the speaker’s quick progress to the next sentence denies the opportunity to respond. It opens the door to conversation and then slams it shut. Moreover, the speaker’s gung-ho continuation to the next sentence implies the listener’s agreement, even though they are allowed no time to think the question over. In the example above, the listener is basically coerced into accepting a historic interpretation as a precondition to the second sentence’s question. I call shenanigans. Perhaps we should only ask questions if we are prepared to listen to peoples’ responses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 04:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/english/2015/02/01/right/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/english/2015/02/01/right/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Un Hombre Normal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the nice things about listening to songs in different languages is that that nothing seems immediately hackneyed (because it’s hard to understand what the hell is going on). And if you go through the trouble to actually decode the lyrics, there’s a good chance that cheeseball pop’s cliches won’t be as off-putting as they are in your native language. They’ll be hard-won and unfamiliar (as opposed to the easily-understood and familiar cliches of a native tongue). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this reason — and probably a few others — I am able to unabashedly enjoy songs like Espinoza Paz’ “&lt;a href=&quot;http://grooveshark.com/#!/s/Un+Hombre+Normal/3XV2ft?src=5&quot;&gt;Un Hombre Normal&lt;/a&gt;”, in which Mr. Paz explains to his former significant other that he’s going to pretend to be a functioning member of society after their breakup. Here is a highly unpoetic translation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;lyrics english&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;section&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;(talking)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;My love, through this song&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;I want to tell you how I feel&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;(singing now)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;I know that nothing will happen if you don&#39;t see me tomorrow&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;I have to accept that you&#39;re not interested in this this romantic anymore&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;I was never your priority or your center of attention&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;I have to accept that — if I was ever in your heart — I&#39;m not there anymore&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;section&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;(chorus)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;I&#39;ll pretend to be a normal guy that can live without you; that doesn&#39;t feel horrible&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;And I&#39;m going to smile so that my sadness passes unnoticed.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;Maturely, I&#39;m going to pull back.&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;And for the first time I promise not to cry&lt;/span&gt; 
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;And I&#39;m going to smile so that my sadness passes unnoticed.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;section&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;As I said to the city [?] when you vanished:&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;how can I accept that — if I was ever in your heart — I&#39;m not in there anymore?&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;section&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;(chorus)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;section&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;(talking)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;I only wanted you to know how I felt through this song.&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;But that&#39;s it; that&#39;s it&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;lyrics spanish&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;section&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;(hablando)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;Corazon, a través de esta canción, quiero decirte como me siento&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;section&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;(cantando)&lt;/span&gt;      
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        se que nada pasará &lt;br /&gt; si mañana no me ves
      &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        tengo que asimilar &lt;br /&gt;
        que por este soñador &lt;br /&gt;
        ya no tienes interes
      &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        nunca fui tu prioridad&lt;br /&gt;
        ni tu centro de attención
      &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        tengo que asimilar&lt;br /&gt;
        que si estuve ya no estoy &lt;br /&gt;
        dentro de tu corazon
      &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        (coro)&lt;br /&gt;
        me haré pasar&lt;br /&gt;
        por un hombre normal&lt;br /&gt;
        que puede estar sin tí&lt;br /&gt;
        que no se siente mal
      &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        y voy a sonreir&lt;br /&gt;
        para que pase desapercibida mi tristeza
      &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        con maduréz&lt;br /&gt;
        me voy a retirar
      &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        y por primera vez&lt;br /&gt;
        prometo no llorar
      &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        y voy a sonreir
        para que pase desapercibida
        mi tristeza
      &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        que le digo a la ciudad&lt;br /&gt;
        por tu desaparición
      &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        como puedo asimilar&lt;br /&gt;
        que si estuve ya no estoy&lt;br /&gt;
        dentro de tu corazón      
      &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        (coro)
      &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        (hablando)
      &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        A través de esta canción&lt;br /&gt;
        Solo quería que supieras como me siento
      &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;unit&quot;&gt;
        Pero sola eso, sola eso
      &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2015 04:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/translation/cheeseball%20pop/2015/01/25/un-hombre-normal/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/translation/cheeseball%20pop/2015/01/25/un-hombre-normal/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Colear [verb]</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I first encountered the phrase “wag the dog” in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wag_the_Dog&quot;&gt;movie with that title&lt;/a&gt;. Being like 10 years old at the time, I didn’t realize that it was an expression and never stopped to consider what it actually meant (this happens to me a lot). People argue about the term’s definition on the Internet, but I think the idea is that some lesser entity is uncharacteristically controlling a larger one. So if an intern is manipulating his/her boss, that would be an instance of a tail wagging the dog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to a Spanish word that implies a tail-wagging entity. &lt;em&gt;Colear&lt;/em&gt; is a verb that means &lt;em&gt;to wag its tail&lt;/em&gt;, and it comes from the noun &lt;em&gt;cola&lt;/em&gt;, which can translate to &lt;em&gt;tail&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;line/queue&lt;/em&gt;, and a few more vulgar things. The verb is used more excitingly in the figurative sense: past events can wag their tails, i.e. have lasting repercussions. So, for example, you could say something like “&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran%E2%80%93Contra_affair&quot;&gt;the Iran-Contra affair&lt;/a&gt; still wags its tail.” &lt;em&gt;El escándalo Irán-Contra todavía colea&lt;/em&gt;. Amazing, no?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those keeping score at home: &lt;em&gt;cola&lt;/em&gt; (tail) comes from the Latin &lt;em&gt;cauda&lt;/em&gt; (tail), which is also where we get the English-by-way-of-Italian &lt;em&gt;coda&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coda_%28music%29&quot;&gt;a concluding section of a musical work&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a floating dog with a spinning tail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/floating_dog.gif&quot; alt=&quot;doge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 04:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2015/01/24/colear/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2015/01/24/colear/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aflorar [verb]</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As you may have noticed, updates have been less frequent (read: absent) this week. Work has begun with the new year, which means less time for ill-informed speculation on and flagrant abuses of language.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years back, I became enamored with the word “efflorecence,” which can denote “the state or a period of flowering.” I employed it figuratively, attempting to capture manifestations of various phenomena as, well, flowers. Professors raised eyebrows, but Dictionary.com/Random House has &lt;a href=&quot;http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/efflorescence?s=t&quot;&gt;sort of conceded it&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;noun&lt;br /&gt;
…&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;2. an example or result of growth and development:&lt;br /&gt;
These works are the efflorescence of his genius.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, I won’t say that I was using it the book, but I was demonstrating a Shakespearean willingness to stretch the bounds of language, right? No? Whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So imagine my surprise when I encountered the apparently similar &lt;em&gt;aflorar&lt;/em&gt; in a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2015/01/09/actualidad/1420835057_908812.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; about Spanish Muslims in the aftermath of the Paris terrorist attacks: &lt;em&gt;“A pie de calle, la desconfianza y los prejuicios hacia los musulmanes &lt;strong&gt;aflora&lt;/strong&gt; con especial intensidad desde hace tres días.”&lt;/em&gt; This roughly translates* to “Since three days ago, suspicion and prejudice towards Muslims in the street has &lt;strong&gt;surfaced&lt;/strong&gt; with unique intensity.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;aflorar&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;effloresce&lt;/em&gt; bear a certain surface resemblance (each starts with a vowel, then continues to a bloom-related-term that starts with an “f”), &lt;em&gt;aflorar&lt;/em&gt; is a subtly different word. First, we look at &lt;em&gt;florar&lt;/em&gt;, whose &lt;a href=&quot;http://lema.rae.es/drae/?val=florar&quot;&gt;definition&lt;/a&gt; translates as “said of a plant or of a tree, especially of one that you cultivate in order to harvest its products: to give flower [&lt;em&gt;dar flor&lt;/em&gt;].” This makes sense, but it’s worth noting that the word is particularly suited for plants designed to be harvested (wheat and orange trees spring to mind as examples). This becomes immediately relevant when we look at &lt;em&gt;aflorar&lt;/em&gt;, whose &lt;a href=&quot;http://lema.rae.es/drae/?val=aflorar&quot;&gt;three definitions&lt;/a&gt; translate* as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Sift flour or winnow grain to obtain the best parts thereof [?]  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Said of a seam of a mineral, of a stratum, or a any mineral mass: appear on the land’s surface.  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Said of something hidden, forgotten, in development [?], or in gestation; spring forth, materialize, appear.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So &lt;em&gt;aflorar&lt;/em&gt; may not be just the &lt;em&gt;flowering&lt;/em&gt; of something (definition 3), but also the eventual winnowing of that something’s products (definition 1). The mysterious allure of the third definition is undeniable — particularly because the Spanish word for “hidden” is &lt;em&gt;oculto&lt;/em&gt; — but the third has an attractive workmanlike quality (tempered, of course, by the fact that “flor” is part of the word). Fortunately we can have both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I guess all I needed to do to use efflorescence was switch languages. So be it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
* as always, take all of my “translations” with a grain of salt.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/Kw3Yd0H.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;I have no idea what I&#39;m doing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2015 05:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2015/01/10/aflorar/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2015/01/10/aflorar/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Magia y Palabras</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Full disclosure: I can only find this passage on Twitter. The account’s purported administrator &lt;a href=&quot;https://borgesyyo.wordpress.com/criterio-del-twitter/&quot;&gt;writes that&lt;/a&gt; he may modify some passages to be fit for Twitter. To a neophyte at least, my inconclusive search for the source text seems appropriately Borgesian.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actively learning a foreign language has destabilized a lot of my gut feelings about language. I can still recall some semiotic gymastics from college, and a few years of news consumption has attuned me to public figures’ expansions and modulations of English words, but nothing illustrates language’s arbitrariness quite like learning that &lt;em&gt;lapiz&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;pencil&lt;/em&gt; actually mean the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I turn to this tweet from an account that seeks to spread Borges awareness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Una magia que no estaba en las palabras, sino en lo que las palabras dejaban adivinar, en lo que se traslucía detrás de esas palabras.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Borges, Jorge Luis (@BorgesJorgeL) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BorgesJorgeL/status/441061843076128768&quot;&gt;March 5, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A humble attempt at translation (no guarantees on accuracy, here):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A magic that was not within the words themselves, but in that which the words left to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://lema.rae.es/drae/?val=adivinar&quot;&gt;divined&lt;/a&gt;, in that which one &lt;a href=&quot;http://lema.rae.es/drae/?val=traslucirse&quot;&gt;surmised&lt;/a&gt; behind these words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above translation hinges on two words that I don’t fully understand. The first one is &lt;em&gt;adivinar&lt;/em&gt; (which corresponds to ‘divined’ in my translation), a multilayered word that &lt;a href=&quot;http://lema.rae.es/drae/?val=adivinar&quot;&gt;can mean&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;predict the future or discover the hidden, by means of omens or spells&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;discover something hidden through conjecture &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;correctly solve a puzzle/riddle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;correctly guess something by luck&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;distinguish hazily; distinguish from a distance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The verb “divine” seems horribly antiquated, perhaps because divination itself seems like an antiquated practice. In contemporary use, I’m fairly sure I have only seen it used to attack or discredit (“and what has he divined from the quarterly stats?”). Nonetheless, it’s the best word I can think of for the job. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second tough word is &lt;em&gt;traslucir&lt;/em&gt;. This one &lt;a href=&quot;http://lema.rae.es/drae/?val=traslucir&quot;&gt;can mean&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surmise or infer something based on some antecedent or sign&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Said of an object: be translucent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this novice’s judgement, inferances via &lt;em&gt;traslucir&lt;/em&gt; seem more scientific than inferences via &lt;em&gt;adivinar&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;traslucir&lt;/em&gt; has &lt;em&gt;antecedents&lt;/em&gt;, for Pete’s sake!). Perhaps @BorgesJorgeL used these two terms as complements. The mystical &lt;em&gt;adivinar&lt;/em&gt; and more logical &lt;em&gt;traslucir&lt;/em&gt; combine to get at the weird, structured haziness of language comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 08:46:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/borges/quotations/translation/2015/01/02/magia/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/borges/quotations/translation/2015/01/02/magia/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Year&#39;s Terms and Conditions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: I translate and reproduce Eduardo Salles’ work in this post. In a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://cultura.elpais.com/cultura/2014/11/28/actualidad/1417138258_495568.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, he said that it’s cool: “Que sus imágenes estén por la red, a veces sin crédito, no le molesta. Para él internet es ‘agarrar, hacer y repetir’.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not acquainted with the work of the Mexican artist Eduardo Salles, you should be. He draws unbelievably clever cartoons on his site &lt;a href=&quot;http://cinismoilustrado.com/&quot;&gt;Cinismo Ilustrado&lt;/a&gt;, which, owing to their relatively small amount of text, can be feasibly enjoyed (rather than slogged through) by language learners. Here, for example, is a simple one in which brands and branded concepts are rendered as wrestling masks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/heroes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;sundays&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salles just put out a list of terms and conditions for the new year, which I really liked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/terms-and-conditions.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;terms and conditions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it’s so text-heavy, I thought I’d take a stab at a translation (uncertainty is marked with [?]).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following is an (attempted) translation of Eduardo Salles’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://cinismoilustrado.com/image/106620128073&quot;&gt;work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;new-year&quot;&gt;New Year&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;terms-and-conditions&quot;&gt;Terms and Conditions&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s terms and conditions have changed. Please read the new terms and conditions in order to begin the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a. The New Year does not promise to actualize your intentions, goals, objectives, desires, fantasies, or any other imagined projections. The achievement thereof is your sole responsibility, and is subject to changing circumstances during the year [?].&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
b. The New Year does not promise to fulfill your expectations, whatever they may be. Neither is it subject to fulfill economic, political, social, technological, or cultural predictions.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
c. The New Year is not responsible for losses, sicknesses, bankruptcies, layoffs, weight and size gains, romantic disappointments, existential crises, academic problems, or whatever other misfortune one might suffer during its passage.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
d. The New Year is not obligated to be better than The Old Year. All types of catastrophe – natural (hurricanes, earthquakes, fires, floods) and anthropogenic (armed conflicts, currency devaluations, social instability, and Michael Bay movies) – can happen at any moment.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
e. The conditions of the New Year are subject to change without prior warning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;form class=&quot;new-year-terms&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
    &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; name=&quot;terms&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;label name=&quot;terms&quot;&gt;
      I have read and agreed to the terms and conditions of the New Year.
    &lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a class=&quot;button&quot; id=&quot;continue&quot;&gt; Continue &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;a class=&quot;button&quot; id=&quot;mierda&quot;&gt; Screw this &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 03:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/translation/2014/12/31/el-ano-nuevo/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/translation/2014/12/31/el-ano-nuevo/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>BBC Mundo Noticias — Resumen De 2014</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://emp.bbc.co.uk/emp/embed/smpEmbed.html?playlist=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bbc.co.uk%2Fmundo%2Fmeta%2Fdps%2F2014%2F12%2Femp%2F141218_video_2014_resumen_noticias2_ms.emp.xml&amp;amp;title=Cu%C3%A1les%20fueron%20las%20noticias%20m%C3%A1s%20impactantes%20de%202014&amp;amp;product=news&amp;amp;lang=es&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2014 03:41:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/video/news/2014/12/29/noticias-del-a%C3%B1o/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/video/news/2014/12/29/noticias-del-a%C3%B1o/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Amigos del Alma and The Pseudocalque</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, common turns of phrase translate word for word (&lt;em&gt;palabra por palabra&lt;/em&gt;). Wikipedia says that this phenomenon is called a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calque&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;calque&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so I’ll be ill-informedly using that term (full disclosure: I don’t know linguistics or anything like that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These parallel expressions get more fun as they get more figurative – your boss will put the brakes on a project, while &lt;em&gt;su jefe pondrá&lt;/em&gt; [will put] &lt;em&gt;freno&lt;/em&gt; [brake] &lt;em&gt;al projecto&lt;/em&gt;. Wikipedia mentions “skyscraper” as an example; in Spanish, they are &lt;em&gt;rascacielos&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;rascar&lt;/em&gt;: v. to scrape, &lt;em&gt;cielo&lt;/em&gt;: n. sky). Calques like these are a blast because they bore holes through walls between languages (or vocabularies, at least), and – for the short span of a synaptic firing – make you feel like you actually understand Spanish or Chinese or whatever. Foreign languages offer many deeper pleasures, but the calque is instantly gratifying. They’re the cotton candy of language learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is the curious case of what – for lack of a better term – you might call pseudocalques. These phrases employ metaphors that resonate across multiple languages, but aren’t word for word matches. They have wrinkles that make you reflect on language a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example: I &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g0FhbwViHiU&quot;&gt;ran across&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;amigo del alma&lt;/em&gt;  yesterday. This translates literally to “friend of the soul”, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wordreference.com/es/en/translation.asp?spen=alma&quot;&gt;can mean&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;(friendship) kindred spirit/very close friend  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;(romantic) soulmate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While “soulmate” is commonly used to describe romantic partners in English, I know of no English construction that describes a friendship between people with form-fitted souls, which is a real shame (Spanish also has &lt;em&gt;hermano de alma&lt;/em&gt;, or “brother of the soul”). In English, you can call someone a “best friend,” but that just ranks them among other friends. You can call someone “like a brother,” but that’s more about loyalty and commitment. “Kindred spirit” is nice, but leaves friendship out of the equation entirely (you’d be sorted into the same bucket as a kindred spirit, but there’s no telling whether or not you’d get along in there). The closest thing I can think of is the antiquated “bosom buddy,” which is just repulsive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s the romantic definition! To a non-native speaker at least, &lt;em&gt;amigo del alma&lt;/em&gt;’s layering of friendly and romantic meanings captures relationships in which your significant other is your best friend. The increasingly popular “partner” gets at this sense a little bit, but certainly introduces businesslike overtones into romantic relationships (which &lt;em&gt;amigos del alma&lt;/em&gt; emphatically does not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will leave a longer post about why American society is afraid of friend soulmates for another day. For now, here is Roberto Carlos singing “Tu Eres Mi Amigo Del Alma”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/hQLjP-HWabw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;see-also&quot;&gt;See also:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This this &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_calques&quot;&gt;list of calques&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2014 04:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2014/12/28/amigo-del-alma/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2014/12/28/amigo-del-alma/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Honduras [noun]</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The upshot of having a 3rd grade vocabulary is that burying your head in the dictionary yields whole lot of notable secondary definitions. Who would have thought, for example, that the Spanish word for wife (&lt;em&gt;esposa&lt;/em&gt;) would turn into &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wordreference.com/es/en/translation.asp?spen=esposas&quot;&gt;handcuffs&lt;/a&gt; when pluralized!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nation of Honduras presents a less hilarious instance of this – &lt;em&gt;honduras&lt;/em&gt; translates to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wordreference.com/es/en/translation.asp?spen=honduras&quot;&gt;depths&lt;/a&gt; (which is a pretty metal name for a country). The name is of uncertain provenance, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honduras#Etymology&quot;&gt;wikipedia says&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The name could either refer to the bay of Trujillo as an anchorage, &lt;em&gt;fondura&lt;/em&gt; in the Leonese dialect of Spanish, or to Columbus’s alleged quote that “Gracias a Dios que hemos salido de esas Honduras” (“Thank God we have departed from those depths”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first scenario, it’s kind of like Honduras and Anchorage are cousins!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I leave you with a map showing the nation of Honduras, with a pin on Trujillo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://www.openstreetmap.org/export/embed.html?bbox=-89.69238281249999%2C12.586732432464062%2C-82.2216796875%2C19.16592425362801&amp;amp;layer=cyclemap&amp;amp;marker=15.897942401022103%2C-85.95703125&quot; style=&quot;border: 1px solid black&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2014 07:53:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2014/12/25/honduras/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/vocabulary/2014/12/25/honduras/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sobre Pon Sal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog’s title comes from a little song which taught me various irregular forms of the second person imperative in Spanish. It goes something like this (sung to the tune of jingle bells):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;di haz ve&lt;br /&gt;
di haz ve&lt;br /&gt;
pon sal se ten ven&lt;br /&gt;
di haz ve&lt;br /&gt;
di haz ve&lt;br /&gt;
pon sal se ten ven  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed pretty appropriate with it being Christmas Eve day and all, y eso es.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2014 07:53:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://ponsal.com/meta/2014/12/24/sobre-ponsal/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ponsal.com/meta/2014/12/24/sobre-ponsal/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
